changes in your diet not only affect you
physically physiologically inside but
also mentally how will you think
psychologically how well you feel but
you'll never know just how good you can
feel until you put it to the test and
try eating healthier welcome to the
nutrition facts podcast I'm your host Dr
Michael Greger today I'm on my treadmill
answering a wide variety of your
questions everything from the
versatility of purple sweet potato
powder to the benefits of a fermented
soy food called natto and the best way
to manage menopause symptoms
first off Jimmy asks would you recommend
using purple oh purple sweet potato
powder to mix with the orange or the
white ones when you can't find purple oh
that's a what a cool idea
um yeah if you're a purple sweet potato
powder it just has one ingredient purple
sweet potato fantastic I mean you don't
have to mix it with orange or white you
can mix in a smoothie you can
in fact in my uh upcoming book how not
to age out in December 2023 I have a
recipe for Okinawan smoothie which is
based on purple sweet potatoes but yeah
if you didn't have purple sweet and
rabbits people purple sweet potatoes you
can add purple sweet potato powder you
can add it to oatmeal or add it to
anything
um so yeah fantastic
um super so has all the wonderful stuff
the sweet potatoes have plus those those
berry anthocyanins
um which are so important for
um a brain health and all sorts of other
things and so yeah that's great I didn't
even know such a thing existed but I'm
totally gonna look into it cool all
right next up
ammo asks I was put on medication that
caused me to gain weight uh oh my God
not just gain weight almost double your
weight uh managed to lose weight by
changing medications to the plant-based
diet but okay any advice
um I'm so sorry to hear that and I'm
glad that you've uh changed course so I
wrote an entire book just for you how
not to diet
um all the proceeds from all my books
are all done in the charity so go to
your local public library and get how
not to diet
um on in hardcover or audiobook or ebook
um and it talks about it says you
already it looks like you're already um
eating healthy but then there's all
sorts of things you can add on to a
healthy diet to accelerate the loss of
body fat because we want to get you back
down to where you were before so so glad
to um
to uh to be able to help next up
okay Llewellyn says
cholesterol is High
um even though they've cut out the meat
eggs and dairy and trying to watch what
they eat needs to be on a stand what
else is out there that is better than
drugs okay so there's all sorts of
things uh so um the first step uh is to
get rid of foods they increase your
cholesterol and so there's three food
components increased cholesterol and
that's uh saturated fat trans fats and
dietary cholesterol so you've already
eliminated
um uh
well you've limited dietary cholesterol
um by eating vegan but there are still
plant sources Etc I've had like coconut
oil palm corn oil palm oil found a lot
of vegan junk food
um so you'd want to stay away from that
um and then trans fats
um been well actually moved from the U.S
food supply but if you're in a you know
uh this question is coming from another
country where they still have this
partially hydrogenated oils
um that would be something to stay away
from as well and usually just by doing
that will bring your cholesterol down so
average cholesterol uh people eating
vegan about average total cholesterol is
about 140.
um we want to get it below kind of 150.
um
if your doctor's talking about studs
your cholesterol is probably way above
that
um so unless you're just doing a lot of
coconut oil or something then the next
step would be to add food should dye
that actively pull cholesterol from your
body and so that was the thinking behind
Dr David Jenkins portfolio diet out of
the University of Toronto
um where the he came up with a portfolio
of different foods that were that pull
cholesterol from the body using
different mechanisms and so I have kind
of this additive effect and so you know
once you know so part of the portfolio
of eating a lot of soluble fiber rich
foods slimy foods like oatmeal okra
eggplant Etc
um nuts and seeds all sorts of things to
pull your cholesterol down and so then
you've eliminated foods to increase your
cholesterol added Foods actually draw
down your cholesterol and the portfolio
diet should be working well as these
first generation statins
um and uh if it's not then you really
should start looking for secondary
causes of hyper cholesterolemia so for
example undirected thyroid gland can
jack your cholesterol up even if you're
eating really healthy
um excess abdominal adiposity there's a
whole bunch of things you can your
doctor can look at
um before
um
before going to pharmacological options
okay Yogi says does long pepper
increases
absorbed like black pepper oh such a
cool question okay
okay gun pepper Polly so it's uh it's in
the same black pepper family but it has
um I may have seenolytic properties
um
um which is one of the Aging Pathways so
I talk about
um adding long pepper to one's diet
um and uh that's one of the
recommendations in my upcoming book how
not to age something I've done in my own
diet
um and the question is does it increase
absorption of turmeric I don't think so
well does it have piperine that's a good
question
so I believe what um
what's what's increasing absorption of
it's not so much the absorption of
turmeric it's the
suppression of the detoxification of
curcumin so basically there's something
in black pepper that suppresses your
liver's detox enzymes which normally
would
um detoxify this curcumin which is like
what is this in the body
um which is the bright yellow pigment in
turmeric and so when you suppress your
liver's ability to remove it you get
higher levels in your bloodstream by
like you know two thousand percent
um and
so so I think it's the piperine which is
kind of the
the the the spicy compound in black
pepper long pepper has a different
flavor it has a more kind of a numbing
white Szechuan pepper kind of flavor so
um it may not have pepper and if it
doesn't I would not expect it to have
the same impact on your liver that would
increase the bioavailability of the
compound in turmeric
okay next question bit finesse
says uh whoa on a diet three pounds of
greens that's a lot of Greens Greens are
really light so three bones of greens a
massive amount of greens two Buns of
sweet potatoes oh that sounds you're
making me hungry some berries during the
evening
one to four percent fat whoa that's
extraordinarily low-fat diet I mean
Okinawa is only like nine percent fat
and uh although yeah so it's about 10
it's probably 10 to 15 is probably
normal for the human species but that's
extraordinarily low but I ate one third
of a pound of mixed nuts allergies face
blew up into a child giant cold sore
um
okay so if you're eating that many mixed
nuts obviously you're that it's not that
low in fat unless you were alone fat and
also made nuts and then he had a cold
sore so cold sores
I mean presumably is is around the lips
you think of cold sore as opposed to
your face
um cold sores can be uh triggered by Sun
um probably a bunch of different things
um
but not by nuts as far as I'm concerned
it's caused by virus
um herpes virus one
um so yeah uh uh I
um
I would diversify your diet
um you're hitting a few on The Daily
dozen but there's a lot of others you
just hit including nuts but
um
uh known reason to eat a third of a
pound an ounce or a little less than an
ounce a day is perfectly fine sorry
about your cold sore there are some
things you can do about your cold sore
um uh there's not great data about
lysine uh that's it's a supplement
that's touted as being anti-cold Source
but what does work is
um antiviral drugs so um valacyclovir
and acyclovir
um uh even just a day like two doses uh
can work as well as longer courses
um and the earlier the better so you
could if you get cold sores you can have
it on your person uh so you can get a
prescription for it and have it and then
as soon as you feel the tingle or
whatever you know you're gonna get one
you can take it and it reduces uh uh it
reduces uh the duration by about a day
um and then if you keep getting
recurrent cold sores then you can be on
kind of a prophylactic dose of something
like valacyclovir like 500 milligrams a
day
um that's often used for like herpes 2
infection like trying to uh suppress
um genital herpes outbreaks but can also
suppress some cold sores as well
but hopefully you can find ways like you
know sunblock or something if if the Sun
is one of the triggers
um that means you don't have to be on
drugs your whole life fuchsia asks a
menopause and hi LDL 90 days ago oh
wonderful husband and I started the
whole food plant-based Journey his
numbers oh my God wonderful gorgeous 238
to 102 but uh my LDL only works 20
points so well hey 20 points that's
amazing
um or I guess it depends on how high
your LDL was but that's pretty good
um uh just stick with it and it should
continue to come down
um uh and so that's fantastic I mean
just like look some people can eat
crappy foods and their cholesterol
doesn't go up as much as other people
um and they're just kind of lucky that
way
um and so uh difference in genetics can
offer a difference in impact of uh diet
and lifestyle choices and so it's not
that uh you know there's different diets
for different people with different
genetics but it's the you know some
people exercise is healthier than other
people
um uh some people smoking is worse than
for other people you know they have this
predisposition for lung cancer
um and that the you know the tobacco
they're just waiting for those first few
mutations from uh from the cigarette
smoke and so um
so it if you're eating the same kind of
food then it may be just be genetic
differences but you're moving in the
right direction that's the important
thing stick with it
um and uh and uh if you don't come down
to Target then uh you know start
thinking about some of these other
things I talked about with portfolio
diet there's all sorts of things that
lower cholesterol too like black cumin
and I if you just type in cholesterol
into nutrition facts that are all sorts
of stuff come up amlas also lowers
cholesterol is dried Indian Gooseberry
powder so sorts of supplements that can
do it as well
okay Scott says can I exercise while
doing 18 6 intermittent fasting
absolutely you can exercise in fact
if um if you're doing intermittent
fasting to lose weight
um to maintain muscle mass
um on any kind of caloric restriction
exercise is critically important
um
obviously if you're dizzy or lightheaded
you want to be careful
um
but yeah that's fine I mean that kind of
intermittent fasting if you do it if you
do it right meaning that it's early
um uh meaning that you eat earlier in
the day and you know stop eating like in
that case you know before three o'clock
you can get tremendous metabolic
benefits
um I profile this study
um in my time restricted feeding uh
video and I keep looking at it and every
time I read about it because I talked
about it in my how not to age so I have
a whole caloric restriction chapter
um in the how not to age
um every time I see that study I'm just
like baffled by uh how powerful that is
so early time restricted feeding you
know skipping supper or trying to shove
as many calories in the morning as
possible and stopping eating
um early
even if you're eating the same Foods
um can have uh remarkably different
effects thanks to our circadian rhythms
and exercise would be a great uh benefit
to that if you can do it that's great
okay
a Nels Nell's nails says I changed my
mind on fluoride what are my
recommendations
um so I gave a webinar recently talking
about
um community fluoridation and uh new
data
um out of Canada which has got a lot of
people concerned about
um fluoride in the water as a as a
neurodevelopmental neurotoxicant and so
pregnant women
um may want to try to avoid excess
fluoride intake
um but um that's separate from topical
fluoride
which can give you the benefits of
drinking fluoride without the risks and
so I encourage people to stick with
fluoride containing toothpaste but uh
but
um for um but for pregnant women to not
be in testing more fluoride than is
um than you can get away with
um and this is not just me this next
national toxicology
um uh program has come out
um with numerous dress statements
reviewed by the National Academy of
Sciences etc etc
um so it's really kind of going the way
of of of uh it's kind of similar to what
we were kind of in the early 80s with
lead
um where we see a significant detriment
in IQ in uh child mom child pairs with
greater exposures to uh community
fluoridation
okay
Remco says is not how good for your
health and if so what my benefits might
it be
um so natto is a slimy fermented soy
food
um
well it's not so good for you well I
mean
yeah in that it's a
it's a slimy fermented soy food
um I I think uh people think of NADA
they think a particular form of vitamin
k
um it's not necessary to get
um a natto vitamin K your body can make
that kind of vitamin K from the greens
that we eat so we eat dark green leafy
vegetables and get all the vitamin K I
would eat natto if you like eating Nado
otherwise
um probably the healthiest soy food is
probably tempeh
um which has lots of Virgo thionine and
spermidine and all sorts of beneficial
things or edamame another whole soy food
um uh yeah those are probably the
um healthiest sources of soy
um is Stephanie says nutritional yeast
safe to consume have hurt as some type
of issue with formation that harms the
body should not be consumed nutritional
yeast is safe consume except if you have
hidradonitis separativa which is this
nasty autoimmune disease or another
autoimmune disease called Crohn's
disease which is environment type of
inflammatory bowel I've videos on both
of those and why nutrition yeast is not
good for them but good for everybody
else
okay Gabriella
um what is my what is my advice about
managing menopause symptoms oh boy well
that is a huge part of my
um book Hermitage and my preserving your
hormones chapter
um and uh so it depends on which
menopausal symptoms you're talking about
um in terms of weight gain I would
probably go to my how not to diet book
um but in terms of uh kind of uh these
vasoactive symptoms like hot flashes and
flushes and
um uh night sweats that kind of thing
um there are a bunch of options and soy
foods are one of the ways that you can
uh it's probably the first line
treatment for treating symptoms then
there are um
uh can a gender urinary symptoms of
menopause
um which used to be um
can I have different names but um that
that can be treated with uh
non-pharmacologically with uh vaginal
lubricants and moisturizers and I talk
about the benefit the the Best Brands
um and then there are hormonal both
prescriptive non-prescription
um a local hormonal applications and
different things you can eat and so on
down the list but there's lots of things
you can do uh check out the new book at
your local public library when it hits
it out this December okay wild blueberry
what a name there we go
well blueberry asked if I had my blood I
had my blueberries today if I had my
blood checked what values why should I
pay particular attention in order to
find out where the meaning balanced diet
should I test for certain the USPS the
kind of preventive preventive Services
got
um guidelines committee really suggests
just getting a cholesterol checks no
reason to check for vitamins minerals in
particular unless you have particularly
symptomatic or eat kind of or have kind
of a strange diet where we would assume
that you'd be off kilter in some way
um so it's better just eating a healthy
diet and remaining healthy and then
obviously if you're under a problem you
can check for specific things
unfortunately I'm out of time
um but thank you so much and I'll talk
to you again soon
we will love it if you could share with
us your stories about Reinventing Your
Health through evidence-based nutrition
goodnutritionfacts.org testimonials we
may be able to share it on social media
to help Inspire others
if you'd like to see any of the graphs
charts Graphics images or studies
mentioned here go to the nutrition facts
podcast landing page there you'll find
all the detailed information you need
plus links to all the sources we cite
for each of these topics my last two
books were how to survive a pandemic and
my how not to diet cookbook get ready
this year for the launch of how not to
age and of course all the proceeds for
the sales of all my books goes directly
to charity
nutritionfacts.org is a non-profit
science-based Public Service where you
can sign up for free daily updates on
the latest new nutrition research with
bite size videos and articles uploaded
nearly every day everything on the
website is free there are no ads no
corporate sponsorships no Kickbacks is
strictly non-commercial not selling
anything I just put it up as a public
service as a labor of love as a tribute
to my grandmother whose own life was
saved with evidence-based nutrition